<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
	<!ENTITY % wdb.entities SYSTEM "../docbook/wdb_entities.ent">
	%wdb.entities;
]
>

<refentry id='gribLoad1'>
	
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>gribLoad</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
	</refmeta>
	
	<refnamediv>
		<refname>gribLoad</refname>
		<refpurpose>Load a &grib; file into the WDB database. It is a part of the WDB
			system.</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>
	
	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>gribLoad</command>
			<arg choice='opt'>OPTIONS</arg>
			<arg choice='req'>GRIBFILE1</arg>
			<arg choice='opt'>GRIBFILE2... GRIBFILEN</arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>
	
	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		
		<para>gribLoad loads the contents of the given &grib; file(s) into the wdb database. The
			database must be up and running for this program to work, unless one of the options
			--help or --list have been given on the command line.</para>
		
		<para>Normally, a grib file will only be loaded into the database if it already has the
			file's area in it's database. If you want to load a file with an unknown field
			definition, you must sepcify the option --loadPlaceDefinition. This will load
			the &grib; file's place definition into the database before loading
			data.</para>
		
	</refsect1>
	
	<refsect1>
		<title>Options</title>
		
		<variablelist>
			<?dbfo list-presentation="blocks"?>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--help</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Produces the help message and then exits.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--version</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Produce version information and then exits.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--logfile FILENAME.LOG</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set output logfile. The default is to print to stdout</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--loglevel LEVEL</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Sets the logging level, from 1 (most) to 5 (least)</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-l</term>
				<term>--list</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This lists the contents of the file, instead of inserting the
						data into the database</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-m M</term>
				<term>--loadMode=M</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the load mode to M. The loading mode determines which
						codespace is used to decode the data internally in the database.
						The default loading mode is 1; the standard english codespace used
						by met.no. 0 is the testing codespace, used by (almost) all of the
						test code in WDB.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--time</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Print the time used by the gribLoad process.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--loadPlaceDefinition</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Loads the place definition of the &grib; file into the database,
						if it does not already exist there. The default behavior of the
						gribLoad application is to report an error if the place definition
						(grid) of the file being loaded is not in the database.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>--overwrite</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Overwrites existing data in the database. The default behavior
						of the gribLoad application is to refuse to load duplicate
						data.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-d DBNAME</term>
				<term>--database=DBNAME</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Specify the database name to connect to (e.g., wdb).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-h DBHOST</term>
				<term>--host=DBHOST</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Specify the database host to connect to (e.g.,
						somehost.met.no).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-u DBUSER</term>
				<term>--user=DBUSER</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Specify the WDB user to connect as. The database user must have
						access to the wdb_grib role (this is will usually be the case if the
						gribLoad process is being run by the creator of the
						database).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>-p DBPORT</term>
				<term>--port=DBPORT</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Specify the database port to connect to (e.g., 5432).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
		</variablelist>
		
	</refsect1>
	
	<refsect1>
		<title>Exit Status</title>
		
		<para>gribLoad returns 0 to the shell if it finished normally and 1 if a fatal error
			occured during loading (out of memory, files not found, database not found,
			etc.). Note that not being able to load a field is not considered a fatal error; in
			such cases, gribLoad simply logs a warning or error to the log and tries to load the
			next field. </para>
		
	</refsect1>
	
</refentry>
